Guide to the Democratic Socialists of America Records TAM.105
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
- Series IV. Youth Section/Young Democratic Socialists of America, 1987-1995; 0.69 Linear Feet in 1 flat box and 1 manuscript box; 1 videocassettes (vhs); 4 audiocassettes
  This series contains materials from the youth and student section of the DSA from its early days as the Youth Section to its current iteration as the Young Democratic Socialists of America (YDSA). Materials include Executive Committee and National Coordinating Committee minutes, memos and mailings, chapter updates, event materials (conference programs, rally and march flyers, and articles/clippings about events), information on internship programs (applications), fundraising and outreach documents (correspondence and mailings, fundraising event invitations, and membership brochures), organizing manuals, resolutions, and events by related organizations (Student Action Union, Campus Labor Institute). Also included are audiovisual recordings of conferences.
  - Michael Harrington Speech -- Convention, Cleveland, 1987 (Box 162, Vhs 105_0203)
  - Summer Convention, August 18, 1989 (Box 155, Audiocassette 105_0105)
  - Convention, November 11-12, 1995 (Box 155, Audiocassette 105_0099-105_101)
- Series V. Staff and Administrative Materials, 1997; 0.25 Linear Feet in 1 flat box; 6 audiocassettes
  This series mostly consists of materials created by the staff at the national office. These materials include general financial records (mostly budgets), internal memos, staff meeting minutes, and directors' correspondence and reports. Additionally, there is biographical material on Michael Harrington, who served as chair of DSA from its inception to his death. Items include correspondence between Michael Harrington and publishers, copies of his CV, a published article by his wife, and an early photograph.
  - Staff Retreat, January 1997 (Box 155, Audiocassette 105_0093-105_0098)
- Series VI. Conventions, 1983-2002; 3.77 Linear Feet in 5 manuscript boxes and 2 flat boxes; 25 audiocassettes; 2 videocassettes (hi8); 18 videocassettes (vhs)
  This series contains materials related to DSA's National Convention, which is currently held every other year. Delegates from across the country elect the members of the National Political Committee (NPC), which acts as the highest decision-making body between conventions. Materials cover the first convention through conventions in the 2010s, and include programs, agendas, mailings to speakers, speeches, papers delivered, registration materials, facilities information, press packets, resolutions, and audiovisual recordings of speeches and conference sessions.
  - Midwestern Socialist-Feminist Conference, Chicago -- Zillah Eisenstein and Holly Graff, November 6, 1983 (Box 155, Audiocassette 105_0091-105_0092)
  - National Convention, Washington, D. C., December 1987 (Box 158, Vhs 105_0159)
  - National Convention -- Barbara Ehrenreich, 1989 (Box 159, Vhs 105_0166, Box 163, Vhs 105_0213)
  - National Convention -- Bogdan Denitch and Joanne Borkon, 1990 (Box 163, Vhs 105_0212)
  - Socialist Scholars Conference, April 6-7, 1991 (Box 164, Audiocassette 105_0221-105_0222)
  - National Convention, Chicago, November 9-10, 1991 (Box 155, Audiocassette 105_0106-105_0107, 105_0109, Box 159, Vhs 105_0168, Box 162, Vhs 105_0202)
  - National Convention, Los Angeles, November 12-14, 1993 (Box 164, Audiocassette 105_0223-105_0232, Box 156, Vhs 105_0131, Box 159, Vhs 105_0167)
  - Socialist Scholars Conference, April 7-9, 1995 (Box 164, Audiocassette 105_0233-105_0237)
  - Unidentified Conference Sessions, August 11, 2000 (Box 155, Hi8 105_0122-105_0123)
  - National Convention, 2001 (Box 158, Vhs 105_0154-105_0157)
  - Low Wage Economy Conference, September 2002 (Box 159, Vhs 105_0172-105_0173)
  - Unidentified Conference Sessions, undated (Box 155, Audiocassette 105_0108, 105_0112-105_0113, Box 159, Vhs 105_0169-105_0171)
- Series IX. Events and Publicity, 1967-2001; 6.08 Linear Feet in 4 flat boxes, 1 record carton, 1 tall manuscript box, and 8 manuscript boxes; 39 sound tape reels; 59 audiocassettes; 61 videocassettes (vhs); 6 videocassettes (hi8); 6 videocassettes (u-matic)
  This series consists of event and program materials which reflect DSA's mission of reform through direct action. Included are planning materials (correspondence and memos, budgets, schedules, and volunteers) for various projects and events sponsored by DSA, such as the Speakers' Bureau, Solidarity Day, Justice for All, Mobilization Against the Draft rallies, University in Society Project, and National Campaign for Peace in the Middle East. Additionally, there is information on conferences by other organizations such as New Directions, Democratic Alternatives, and International Union of Socialist Youth; and corresponding publicity (flyers, posters, articles, and clippings). Also included are audiovisual recordings of television appearances by DSA leaders, sessions from other organizations' conferences, and lectures and talks.
  - Robert Lekachman -- League for Industrial Democracy, February 24, 1967 (Box 76, Quarter inch audio reel 105_0026-105_0027)
  - Labor Institute Sessions, April 6-7, 1968 (Box 76, Quarter inch audio reel 105_0028-105_0036)
  - Frances Fox Piven and Roy Innis -- "The Urban Crisis: Views from the Left" -- The New School, February 1970 (Box 76, Quarter inch audio reel 105_0003-105_0009)
  - Leon Keyserling and Paul Jennys -- League for Industrial Democracy Trade Union Luncheon -- The New School:, February-March 1970 (Box 76, Quarter inch audio reel 105_0010-105_0014)
  - Yehoshafat Harkabi Speaking at Unknown Event, October 26, 1970 (Box 76, Quarter inch audio reel 105_0015-105_0017)
  - Unidentified Conference, circa 1970 (Box 154, Audiocassette 105_0064-105_0086, Box 155, Audiocassette 105_0087-105_0090)
  - Michael Harrington Debates David Rockefeller, Vice President of Chase Manhattan Bank, 1976; cuid271 (Box 164, Audiocassette 105_0249)
  - Michael Harrington Debates Rep. Jack Kemp in New York, NY, April 25, 1979 (Box 164, Audiocassette 105_0250)
  - Unidentified Conference, Chicago, IL, circa late 1970s (Box 165, Audiocassette 105_0255)
  - Democratic Agenda Rally, August 15, 1980; cuid268 (Box 164, Audiocassette 105_0218)
  - American Public Health Association (APHA) Convention -- Michael Harrington -- "Crisis in the Public Sector: Challenge to the Public Health", 1981 (Box 165, Audiocassette 105_0256-105_0257)
  - "Tax Policy and the Economy: A Debate between Michael Harrington and Jack Kemp -- Moderated by Leonard Silk", March 20, 1983 (Box 157, Vhs 105_0138)
  - Harrington Lecture at Department of Political Science at Loyola University of Chicago, 1985 (Box 165, Audiocassette 105_0258-105_0259)
  - Crossfire with Michael Harrington, January 13, 1986 (Box 156, Vhs 105_0133)
  - New Directions Conference, Washington, D. C., May 2-4, 1986; cuid269 (Box 155, Audiocassette 105_0114-105_0116, Box 164, Audiocassette 105_0219, Box 157, Vhs 105_0144-105_0147, Box 158, Vhs 105_0149-105_0151, Box 162, Vhs 105_0200-105_201)
  - Democratic Alternatives Conference, February 27, 1987 (Box 164, Audiocassette 105_0220)
  - Senate Hearing on Poverty, October 7, 1987 (Box 159, Vhs 105_0174, Box 160, U-matic 105_0182)
  - Michael Harrington at Jewish Labor Board Luncheon, New York, NY, October 15, 1987 (Box 165, Audiocassette 105_0260)
  - Michael Harrington -- "The New American Poverty" -- Rosemont College, October 29, 1987 (Box 157, Vhs 105_0141, 105_0146, Box 158, Vhs 105_0153, Box 162, Vhs 105_0197, 105_0204, 105_0209)
  - Justice for All -- Public Service Spots and "America", 1987 (Box 163, Quarter inch audio reel 105_0037, Box 161, Vhs 105_0194)
  - "Poverty in America" -- More Than the News, Ithaca, 1987 (Box 156, Vhs 105_0132)
  - Michael Harrington at Boston DSA Awards Dinner, June 2, 1988 (Box 162, Vhs 105_0207)
  - Interview with Kris Rondeau of Harvard Clerical and Technical Workers Union, June 13, 1988; cuid273 (Box 165, Audiocassette 105_0261)
  - Unidentified Program with Michael Harrington, June 30, 1988 (Box 158, Vhs 105_0158, Box 162, Vhs 105_0205)
  - Michael Harrington Interview [Tape 2], August 2, 1988 (Box 164, Audiocassette 105_0251)
  - Howard Cosell Interviews Michael Harrington, August 19, 1988 (Box 164, Audiocassette 105_0252)
  - Bodgan Denitch and Michael Harrington at City University of New York, October 1988 (Box 161, Vhs 105_0192)
  - Michael Harrington -- "Politics of Social Welfare in the 1990s" -- GWB School of Social Work, Washington University in St. Louis, March 23, 1989 (Box 163, Vhs 105_0210)
  - Michael Harrington on "Towards a New Socialism" and "The Next Left", April 12, 1989 (Box 157, Vhs 105_0136, 105_0139, 105_0148, Box 160, U-matic 105_0178)
  - Michael Harrington Remembrance on NPR's Morning Edition, August 2, 1989 (Box 165, Audiocassette 105_0254)
  - Michael Harrington Memorial Service, September 15, 1989 (Box 156, Vhs 105_0128, Box 162, Vhs 105_0208)
  - "On the Move: Victory at 1199" -- Bread and Roses Cultural Project, September 13, 1990 (Box 161, Vhs 105_0189)
  - Bernie Sanders in Baltimore -- Sponsored by DSA and VE, May 7, 1991 (Box 163, Vhs 105_0217)
  - California This Week, KRON Ch. 4 -- "Canadian Healthcare", October 13, 1991 (Box 156, Vhs 105_0130)
  - 80th Birthday for Ben Dobbs, February 23, 1992 (Box 163, Vhs 105_0214)
  - Paul Pinsky, Mary Jo Kilroy, David Kusnick, and Bob Fitrakis, June 14, 1992 (Box 164, Audiocassette 105_0245)
  - Billy Bragg and Pete Seeger: Songs of Protest Benefit Concert, 1992 (Box Shared Tamiment 037, 2 inch audio reel 105_0183, Box 161, Vhs 105_0193)
  - Presentation by Ellen Braune and Cajuste Lexiuste on Haiti at Committee in Solidarity with the People of El Salvador (CISPES), July 20, 1994 (Box 165, Audiocassette 105_0262)
  - Federal Judge Denies FCC Injunction Against Micro-Radio -- San Francisco Liberation Radio, January 20, 1995 (Box 165, Audiocassette 105_0263)
  - Frances Fox Piven -- "Women in the Welfare State," Portland, ME, March 10, 1995 (Box 164, Audiocassette 105_0246)
  - Anti-Contract Demonstration -- Fairbanks, Alaska, April 8, 1995 (Box 163, Vhs 105_0211)
  - Michael Lerner and Cornel West -- "Jews and Blacks: Let the Healing/Future Begin," Cambridge, MA, April 24, 1995 (Box 164, Audiocassette 105_0247)
  - Charney Visit to Columbus, September 1995 (Box 156, Vhs 105_0129)
  - Dorothy Healy at Unidentified Event, circa 1995 (Box 155, Audiocassette 105_0104)
  - Cornel West, Kurt Stand, Heidi Hartman, and Bob Fitrakis, circa 1995-1996 (Box 164, Audiocassette 105_0248)
  - Economic Insecurity Hearings, Boston, January-March 1996 (Box 155, Hi8 105_0117-105_0121, Box 156, Vhs 105_0125-105_0127, Box 160, U-matic 105_0179-105_0181, Box 161, Vhs 105_0186)
  - Breaking Bread Events -- Prison Protest and Moratorium Workshop, 1997 (Box 158, Vhs 105_0162, Box 159, Vhs 105_0165)
  - Convocation Awards Dinner, 1997 (Box 159, Vhs 105_0164)
  - Michael Harrington and Today's Other America: Corporate Power and Inequality, 1999 (Box 156, Vhs 105_0124, Box 157, Vhs 105_0137)
  - Cornel West -- "Progressive Politics in These Times: From Vision to Action" -- Mario Savio Memorial Lecture -- University of California, Berkeley Student Union, November 15, 2001 (Box 156, Vhs 105_0135)
  - N. Hill and Michael Harrington, undated (Box 76, Quarter inch audio reel 105_0018-105_0025)
  - "Arguments from the Left", undated (Box 156, Vhs 105_0134)
  - DSA Presents "Enron: The Bankruptcy of Neoliberalism" and Other Discussions, undated (Box 157, Vhs 105_0140)
  - Unidentified Programs with Michael Harrington, undated (Box 157, Vhs 105_0142-105_0143, Box 158, Vhs 105_0152)
  - Barbara Ehrenreich on Donahue, undated (Box 162, Vhs 105_0206)
  - Lacefield and Hall, undated (Box 163, Vhs 105_0216)
  - DSA's Domestic Agenda, undated; cuid270 (Box 164, Audiocassette 105_0244)
  - "Michael Harrington: In His Own Words", undated; cuid272 (Box 164, Audiocassette 105_0253)
  - Opening Session and Industrial Democracy Session, Unknown Conference, undated (Box 165, Audiocassette 105_0264)
  - Shakoor on Multiculturalism; Suzanne Crowell on Mission, undated (Box 165, Audiocassette 105_0265)
  - Joe Schwartz on Identity Politics; Hughes and Lighty on the Economy, undated (Box 165, Audiocassette 105_0266)
  - Frances Fox Piven, Morton Bahr, and Gloria Steinem, undated (Box 165, Audiocassette 105_0267)
  - Unidentified Events or Programs, undated (Box 163, Quarter inch audio reel 105_0038, Box Shared Tamiment 037, Quarter inch audio reel 105_0039, Box 155, Audiocassette 105_0110, Box 158, Vhs 105_0160-105_0161, Box 159, Vhs 105_0175-105_0176, Box 160, U-matic 105_0177, Box 161, Vhs 105_0184-105_0185, 105_0187-105_0188)
- Series XII. Institute for Democratic Socialism/Democratic Socialists of America Fund, 1980; 0.5 Linear Feet in 2 flat boxes; 43 audiocassettes
  This series contains materials related to the Institute for Democratic Socialism (IDS), which was founded in 1978 to help spread democratic socialist ideals through educational materials and activist training. In the mid-1990s, IDS changed its name to the Democratic Socialists of America Fund. Materials consist of conference proposals and programs, correspondence, fundraising materials, and some financial records. Materials also include audio recordings of speeches and panels from the "Eurosocialism and America" conference, a three-day conference in 1980, in which U.S. activists met with international leaders of social democratic and democratic socialist political movements to explore how democratic socialist policy alternatives could benefit the U.S. Notable individuals featured in the recordings include world leaders like Willy Brandt (Germany), Olof Palme (Sweden), Joop den Uyl (Netherlands), Francois Mitterand (France), as well as Michael Harrington, union leader William Winpisinger, Representative Ron Dellums, and Gloria Steinem.
  - "Eurosocialism and America: An International Exchange" Conference, 1980 (Box 154, Audiocassette 105_0040-105_0063, Box 165, Audiocassette 105_0268-105_0286)
- Series XIII. Subject Files, 1988-1989; 1.31 Linear Feet in 3 manuscript boxes; 7 videocassettes (vhs)
  Arrangement
  Arranged alphabetically.
  This series includes printed matter (newsletters, brochures, bulletins, conference materials, and journals) from organizations with which DSA worked and supported, such as the Democratic National Committee, Democratic Party, Mobilization for Survival, and Mobilization Against the Draft. Also covered are topics of interest to DSA and its members, such as pro-democracy movements, international solidarity, and Puerto Rican independence. These materials mostly include clippings and articles but there are a few documentaries as well.
  - "Am I Blue? A Report on the Threat to Excellence at Yale", undated (Box 161, Vhs 105_0191)
  - "Citizens" -- Richard W. Adams, circa 1989 (Box 161, Vhs 105_0190)
  - Cover Up: Behind the Iran Contra Affair, 1988 (Box 162, Vhs 105_0199)
  - "Future Watch", undated (Box 162, Vhs 105_0198)
  - "They'll Never Keep Us Down: The Story of the United Mine Workers of America Struggle at the Pittston Company", undated (Box 161, Vhs 105_0196)
  - United Farm Workers of America -- "Wrath of Grapes" -- Spanish Version, undated (Box 161, Vhs 105_0195)
  - "We All Live Downstream" Project, undated (Box 163, Vhs 105_0215)
- Series XIV: Archived Websites, November 2008-ongoing; 45 websites in 45 archived websites.
  Scope and Content Note
  This series contains the main website, blogs, and subdomains of the Democratic Socialists of America (DSA), dating back to 2008. http://www.dsausa.org/ contains information on their campaigns and programs, which include student debt alleviation, immigrant rights, environmentalism, medicare for all, and the protection of social programs, as well as meeting minutes, chapter information, convention materials, fundraising, their scholarship fund, online store, endorsements, videos, and event listings.
  The main DSA website provides links to many of their projects and campaigns, including the Young Democratic Socialists of America, the National Electoral Committee, the Labor Commission, the Anti-War Think Tank, Ecosocialist working group, the International Committee, the DSA Fund, and the Tech Committee. Specific campaign websites were also captured, including Medicare for All, Close the Camps national action (protesting the detention and mistreatment of migrants and refugees, the separation of migrant families, mass deportation, and raids by Immigration and Customs Enforcement), and Democratic Socialists campaign for Bernie Sanders.
  The series also contains online publications created by the DSA, including Socialist Forum, which intends to facilitate debate and discussion among socialist thinkers and DSA members about ongoing political issues and to develop materials that can be incorporated into future political educational materials; Talking Union blog from the DSA Labor network; Democratic Left, their digital magazine; and "Why Socialists Should Become Teachers" digital pamphlet. The online magazine of the Young Democratic Socialists was known as the Activist, which was captured from 2009-2014.
  It also includes the Bread & Roses caucus website, a national caucus of Marxist organizers in the Democratic Socialists of America committed to helping build an effective DSA rooted in the multiracial working class. The website includes the caucus' platform and action items, and their publication, "The Call." "The Call" is an online publication of the Democratic Socialists of America's Bread and Roses Caucus publishing opinion writing about democratic socialist organizing and administration. The site is also home to a podcast: "The Call Radio" which is available for online streaming. ReligiousSocialism.org is the website for the Democratic Socialists of America's Religion and Socialism Commission, founded by John Court, which seeks to build coalitions between progressive people of different faiths and advance conversations that bridge theology and socialist politics. The site manages regular blogs and podcasts.
  The Emergency Workplace Organizing Committee (EWOC) is a project of the Democratic Socialists of America (DSA) and the United Electrical, Radio and Machine Workers of America (UE) to build a distributed, grassroots organizing program to support workers organizing at the workplace. The website contains an organizing guide, organizer training, example workplace campaign petitions and flyers, organizer request form, and a blog.
  Power for Texas is an action campaign developed by Democratic Socialists of America chapters and working groups in Texas, the DSA for a Green New Deal working group, and public power campaigns in response to the Texas power grid failure in February 2021. The website contains action items, calls for public power and green energy, factsheets, and aid resources for people affected by the crisis.
  The PRO Act Campaign is coordinated by the Democratic Soscialists of America's Green New Deal Campaign Committee (GNDCC) and Democratic Socialist Labor Commission (DSLC). The PRO Act (Protect the Right to Organize), ends the "right to work" laws, legalizes secondary strikes, and promotes green jobs. The website also promotes the Green New Deal legislation and press related to the PRO Act.
  The Green New Deal for Public Schools is a project of the Ecosocialists Working Group of the Democratic Socialists of America. The campaign called for the passing of the Green New Deal or Public Schools Act, which includes funding toward green facilities, educators and support staff, comunity engagement, and accessibility.
  Protect Abortion is a campaign by the Democratic Socialists of America launched after the United State Supreme Court overruled Roe v. Wade and limited the right to abortion nationwide. The website contains information on protect abortion training sessions, videos and images from protests, and a toolkit for chapters.
  The Dish is the online newsletter of the Democratic Socialists of America's Restaurant Organizing Project (ROP). The website contains guidance on forming a union, Starbucks workers organizing accounts, COVID-19 and restaurant workers, and other posts about workers in the food and beverage industry.
  The BDS (Boycott, Divestment, and Sanctions) and Palestine Solidarity Working Group of the Democratic Socialists of America was established in 2019. The working group called for an end to Israel's continued occupation and colonization of historic Palestine; equal rights for Palestinians; and the right of millions of Palestinian refugees to finally return to their home after decades of forced exile. The website contains events and actions, a resource library, an FAQ, a national boycott campaign, and statements regarding their call for Jamaal Bowman's expulsion from the DSA, and other statements surrounding Israeli annexation of Palestine.
  National Political Education Committee was established in 2019 in response to a resolution passed by the National Political Committee of the Democratic Socialists of America. NPEC aimed to help DSA chapters develop the lesson plans, curriculum, and the facilitation skills needed to implement a long-term political education program locally. The website contains curricula created nationally and by local chapters.
  The Democratic Socialists of America International Committee works to establish relationships and provide solidarity with socialist and working class organizations internationally. The majority of their work is focused on anti-imperialism and anti-militarism globally, specifically in Cuba, Venezuela, Ukraine, China, Okinawa, Korea, Brazil, Yemen, and United States military bases. The website contains quarterly reports, political education resources, statements, and videos from panels and other events with international organizers and political activists.
  The Rank-and-File Strategy is an organizing strategy by the Democratic Socialists of America to bring socialists and organized workers together to build class power. The website contains a guide to the strategy and case studies.
  The Green New Deal Slate is a group of Democratic Socialists of America endorsed local candidates running on the Green New Deal platform. Members of the slate, Hugo Soto-Martinez in California, Elisabeth Epps in Colorado, Rachel Ventura in Illinois, and Sarahana Shrestha in New York were elected in the November 2022 general elections.
  Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
  Due to technical or privacy issues, archived websites may not be exact copies of the original website at the time of the web crawl. Certain file types will not be captured dependent on how they are embedded in the site. Other parts of websites that the crawler has difficulty capturing includes Javascript, streaming content, database-driven content, and highly interactive content. Full-Text searches of archived websites are available at https://archive-it.org/organizations/567.
  Accruals
  New site crawls are accrued semiannually. In 2020-2021, https://workerorganizing.org/, http://www.dsausa.org/, https://y.dsausa.org/, https://democraticleft.dsausa.org/ were accrued monthly.
  Appraisal
  Crawl was limited to domains and subdomains of dsausa.org and docs.google.com/document/ in order to remain within the collection scope and data constraints. Robots.txt (a piece of code designed to limit crawler activity within a website) was ignored.
  Audio for the podcasts have been captured, but might not render in the archived copy. Future changes to the Wayback Machine may allow the files to be played.